foreign
we are back with a new episode of the
pitch and I am joined today by our
Superstar Chief science officer Dr Matt
fedorick in this episode we're following
up on all the recent news that you've
probably seen about our 21st annual
Symposium on anti-doping science Matt is
going to give us an inside look at the
purpose of the Symposium and some key
takeaways from this year's Edition Matt
thanks for joining us are you ready to
dive in
yeah hey Avery good to be back on the
pitch no it's been a while all right can
you tell us a little bit about the
founding and purpose of the annual
symposium
yeah sure so we have a long history of
hosting an annual science Symposium that
actually started back in 2002 and the
first one was held in Atlanta and we're
really trying to pull together the
world's experts when it comes to
anti-doping the water accredited lab
directors the anti-doping practitioners
whether that be other scientists or
medical professionals from various
anti-doping organizations and then you
know most importantly bring in outside
experts and with these three groups
really have uh two and a half full days
of sessions where we dive in to a
specific scientific topic of Fairly
narrow focus and then have presentations
and discussions which really aim to come
up with unique Solutions and figure out
where there's gaps that need to be
filled whether that be in policy and
practice or scientific research
awesome I thought this year's theme was
particularly interesting so can you
explain that theme and why it was so
relevant this year
yeah yeah your your uh your point is a
good one it's becoming harder and harder
to come up with new and exciting themes
now that we're in our 20 uh well going
into our 22nd year for next year but the
the theme this year was really focusing
on the elite athlete and trying to
differentiate what is extraordinarily
normal we all know that athletes they
compete in extreme environments and
their physiology and training allows
them to to perform at the highest levels
and then how to how to differentiate
between that and doping or what's
extraordinarily abnormal and so really
diving in and going back to basic
principles when it comes to
understanding you know what's expected
physiology how do athletes perform what
kinds of athletes are we talking about
when we think about the diverse
population of athletes across multiple
Sports and disciplines and then you know
all how all those factors come together
in trying to assess uh performance and
and really is are these different
factors and markers things that we can
understand better in order to identify
when an athlete may be performing
abnormally and using either direct or
indirect detection methods in order to
improve the work that we do
awesome so what were a few of the key
takeaways from the presentations this
year
yeah we had a really diverse group of
speakers and we we started off with our
keynote Dr Mike Joyner he's from the
Mayo Clinic and he talked about kind of
this dystopian athlete of the future
that could possibly run a 150 marathon
and really dove into how athletes are
performing and how that performance has
evolved over time and then what are some
of the factors that can still be
manipulated in order to actually improve
performance uh beyond what could be
expected so that was a a pretty cool way
to kick things off and then we had a
really
um a really varied group of speakers
over 20 different speakers talking about
things
um like stem cells and biologic
treatments we had Dr Rachel Frank who
was from the University of Colorado up
in up in Denver come and speak to us
she's an orthopedic physician we had
other speakers from the water accredited
Labs like Dr Mario theebus talk about
things like what can be expected when
athletes are exposed to different uh
prohibited substances in the environment
and how to differentiate that from True
uh doping and we had other speakers talk
about things like performance Dr James
hopker and some of the really cool
modeling that's going on to try to
understand how to predict performance
and what can be expected and when
performances may be excess performances
that we could use in order to feed into
our current risk assessment models so it
was an awesome conference lots of great
discussion
um and lots of uh outcomes that we're
looking to assess and trying to
determine where do we focus some further
development efforts and investments into
improving the detection and deterrence
method methodologies recurrent employee
cool well I can't wait to hear more
about that but I think that's a wrap for
today at least so thank you so much for
your time that and we will be back for
another episode of the pitch soon
thanks Avery see you later
[Music]